Finding Aid for the Stanley Chase Papers LSC.1090
UCLA Library Special Collections
Stanley Chase papers
circa 1925-2001
1955-1989
UCLA Library Special Collections
Chase, Stanley
LSC.1090
157.2 Linear Feet (105 boxes, 12 oversize boxes, and 27 map folders)
Stanley Chase (1928-) was a theater, film, and television producer. The collection consists of production and business files, original production drawings, posters, press clippings, sound recordings, and scripts from his major projects.
Conditions Governing Access
Open for research. All requests to access special collections materials must be made in advance using the request button located on this page.
Physical Characteristics and Technical Requirements
CONTAINS AUDIOVISUAL MATERIALS: This collection contains both processed and unprocessed audiovisual materials. For information about the access status of the material that you are looking for, refer to the Physical Characteristics and Technical Requirements note at the series and file levels. All requests to access processed audiovisual materials must be made in advance using the request button located on this page.
Provenance/Source of Acquisition
Gift of Stanley Chase, 1967-1968 and 2002.
UCLA Catalog Record ID
UCLA Catalog Record ID: 999642153606533
Expanded Biographical Narrative
Stanley Chase was born Stanley Cohen on May 3, 1928 in Brooklyn, New York. He graduated from New Utrecht High School in 1944, and enlisted in the Navy at age 17. He received his B.A. from New York University in 1949, and immediately pursued graduate study in drama at Columbia University. In 1950 Chase went to work for CBS Television and met Carmen Capalbo, with whom he eventually produced the record-breaking musical off-Broadway hit, The Threepenny Opera. Chase followed the success of that production with three more Broadway plays: The Potting Shed (1957), A Moon for the Misbegotten (1957), and The Cave Dwellers (1957). He also produced a European tour of Free and Easy, a Harold Arlen and Johnny Mercer jazz musical featuring Quincy Jones.
Chase went on to work for various film and television companies, including Metro-Goldwyn Mayer, 1962; the American Broadcasting Company, where he was director of network television program development from 1962-1963; United Artists, where he created and developed the ABC television pilot Inside Danny Baker with Mel Brooks in 1963; Columbia Pictures, where he was a television production head and executive producer from 1963-1964; and Universal Studios, where he was an executive and producer from 1965-1970. Major projects from this period include the Universal Studio television anthology series Bob Hope Presents the Chrysler Theatre for NBC, 1966-1967, and the Universal Studios films The Hell with Heroes (1968) and Colossus: The Forbin Project (1970). Chase founded Stanley Chase Productions, Inc. in 1976 as a motion picture, television production, and distribution company, and was president of that enterprise. Major motion picture projects included High Ballin' (1978), Fish Hawk (1982), and Mack the Knife (1990). Television projects included the made for television movies The Courage of Kavik, the Wolf Dog (1979) and An American Christmas Carol (1980).
Scope and Content
The collection consists of production and business files, original production drawings, posters, press clippings, sound recordings, and scripts documenting Stanley Chase's forty-year career as a producer in theater, film, and television. The production files contain contracts, correspondence, legal documents, memoranda, photographs, publicity materials and other miscellaneous papers. Of particular interest are the files pertaining to Chase's off-Broadway production of Kurt Weill and Berthold Brecht's The Threepenny Opera, and the Broadway plays A Moon for the Misbegotten, The Potting Shed, and The Cave Dwellers at the Bijou Theatre. Important materials from the film series include production files, original production design drawings, and photographs for The Hell with Heroes (1968) and Colossus: The Forbin Project (1970), both created while Chase was an executive producer at Universal Studios. The collection also contains voluminous files related to Stanley Chase Productions, Inc. projects and Chase's work in television, including screenplays, story pitches, and memoranda.
Organization and Arrangement
Arranged in the following series:
Theater, 1946-1989 (34 boxes, 5 oversize boxes, 5 map folders), subseries A-E as follows:
The Threepenny Opera, 1952-1961.
Free and Easy, 1956-1960.
Bijou Theatre files, 1946-1961.
Miscellaneous, 1953-1989.
Playbill programs, ca. 1950-1960.
Film, 1955-2001 (38 boxes, 4 oversize boxes, 20 map folders), subseries A-F as follows:
The Hell with Heroes, 1967-1968.
Colossus: The Forbin Project, 1965-1970.
High Ballin', 1976-1986.
Mack the Knife, 1955-1990.
Miscellaneous productions, ca. 1973-1981.
Scripts, 1956-2001.
Television, 1925-1994 (32 boxes, 1 oversize box, 1 map folder), subseries A-D as follows:
An American Christmas Carol, 1979-1994.
The Courage of Kavik, the Wolf Dog, 1977-1983.
Miscellaneous productions, 1925-1994.
Scripts, 1960-1984.
Audiovisual materials, 1959-1989 (1 box, 2 oversize boxes).
Miscellaneous, 1944 (1 folder, 1 map folder).
Existence and Location of Copies
Digitized materials are available electronically at https://digital.library.ucla.edu/catalog/cjm39000zz-89112.
Items Removed from the Collection
The following eleven reels of film and two videos found among the papers were transferred to the UCLA Film and Television Archive in September 2005 for processing.
¾" videotape: Grace Kelly; The Courage of Kavik, the Wolf Dog; High Ballin'; Fish Hawk; High Ballin' screen tests; Fish Hawk trailers.
VHS videotape: Grace Kelly; An American Christmas Carol.
16mm film: Dream Wife pilot; Inside Danny Baker pilot; Jigsaw pilot; Colossus: The Forbin Project.
35mm film: Frontier Family Adventure (aka Fish Hawk), reel 1 only.
Television producers and directors -- United States -- Archives.; Motion picture producers and directors -- United States -- Archives.; Film scripts.; Television plays.; Theatrical producers and directors -- United States -- Archives.; Chase, Stanley, 1927-2005--Archives.; Stanley Chase Productions.
- Series 1: Theater, 1946-1989.; 34 boxes, 5 oversize boxes, 4 map folders.
  Scope and Contents note
  This series consists of production files and business files, original set design illustrations, posters, press clippings, ephemera, and scripts for musicals and plays produced by Stanley Chase. Arranged in subseries A-E as follows:
  The Threepenny Opera, 1952-1961.
  Free and Easy, 1956-1960.
  Bijou Theatre files, 1946-1961.
  Miscellaneous, 1953-1989.
  Playbills and programs, ca. 1950-1960.
  - Subseries 1A: The Threepenny Opera, 1952-1961.; 13 boxes, 2 oversize boxes, 1 map folder.
    This subseries consists of production files and business files, original set design illustrations, posters, press clippings, ephemera, and scripts from Stanley Chase and Carmen Capalbo's off-Broadway hit, Kurt Weill and Bert Brecht's musical The Threepenny Opera. The show ran a record-breaking six and a half years at the Theatre de Lys, and generated a forty-fold return on the initial investment. It won a Tony Award in 1956 as a distinguished Off-Broadway production. The original order and content of the files was maintained at the time of processing. For audio recordings of the cast production, see Series 4. Audio and visual materials.
    - Operating bills--Week 1., 1954 March 14. (Box 1, Folder 1)
      Operating bills for first week of production. Includes box-office, payroll and general expenses.
    - Operating bills--Week 2., 1954 March 21. (Box 1, Folder 2)
      Operating bills for second week of production. Includes box-office, payroll and general expenses.
    - Operating bills--Week 3., 1954 March 28. (Box 1, Folder 3)
      Operating bills for third week of production. Includes box-office, payroll and general expenses.
    - Operating bills--Week 4., 1954 April 4. (Box 1, Folder 4)
      Operating bills for fourth week of production. Includes box-office, payroll and general expenses.
    - Operating bills--Week 5., 1954 April 11. (Box 1, Folder 5)
      Operating bills for fifth week of production. Includes box-office, payroll and general expenses.
    - Operating bills--Week 6., 1954 April 18. (Box 1, Folder 6)
      Operating bills for sixth week of production. Includes box-office, payroll and general expenses.
    - Operating bills--Week 7., 1954 April 25. (Box 1, Folder 7)
      Operating bills for seventh week of production. Includes box-office, payroll and general expenses.
    - Operating bills--Week 8., 1954 May 2. (Box 1, Folder 8)
      Operating bills for eigth week of production. Includes box-office, payroll and general expenses.
    - Operating bills--Week 9., 1954 May 9. (Box 1, Folder 9)
      Operating bills for ninth week of production. Includes box-office, payroll and general expenses.
    - Operating bills--Week 10., 1954 May 16. (Box 1, Folder 10)
      Operating bills for tenth week of production. Includes box-office, payroll and general expenses.
    - Operating bills--Week 11., 1954 May 23. (Box 1, Folder 11)
      Operating bills for eleventh week of production. Includes box-office, payroll and general expenses.
    - Operating bills--Week 12., 1954 May 30. (Box 1, Folder 12)
      Operating bills for twelfth week of production. Includes box-office, payroll and general expenses.
    - Closing expenses., 1954 June 6. (Box 1, Folder 13)
      General closing expenses.
    - Actors' contracts., 1954. (Box 1, Folder 14)
      Contracts and communications from first cast regarding employment.
    - Advertisement bills and contracts., 1954-1960. (Box 1, Folder 15)
    - Threepenny Opera Touring Company--Offering circular., 1960 July 27. (Box 1, Folder 16)
      Statement of initial offering of limited partnership.
    - Audit portfolios (folder 1 of 2)., 1954-1957. (Box 2, Folder 1)
      Portfolios cover the first and second run of the production.
    - Audit portfolios (folder 2 of 2)., 1954. (Box 2, Folder 2)
      Audit portfolios for limited dates in April, May and June (first run).
    - Marketing., 1955, 1960. (Box 2, Folder 3)
      Marketing materials from the Los Angeles and New York productions.
    - Central Bureau for Registered Addresses., 1956-1957. (Box 2, Folder 4)
      Materials relating to change of address and name of production company managing New York production.
    - Playbills., 1957, 1960. (Box 2, Folder 5)
      Playbills from the New York, Los Angeles and New Jersey productions.
    - Financial summaries., 1958-1960. (Box 2, Folder 6)
      Financial summaries of production prepared by CPA firm, Seidman and Seidman.
    - Trade magazines., 1960. (Box 2, Folder 7)
      Trade magazines and clippings.
    - Magazines, playbills, theater guides., 1955-1956, 1960. (Box 2, Folder 8)
      Contents related to the production of The Threepenny Opera in Los Angeles and New York.
    - Budgets., 1954. (Box 2, Folder 9)
      Documentation relating to budgeting projection and planning.
    - Box office., 1953-1955. (Box 3, Folder 1)
      Correspondence and box office statements related to ticket sales.
    - Business Certificate, bank, tax and Workers' Compensation., 1954-1957. (Box 3, Folder 2)
      Assorted business papers.
    - Investor agreements., 1954. (Box 3, Folder 3)
      Contracts and correspondences between Christopher Productions and investors.
    - Legal correspondence., 1954. (Box 3, Folder 4)
      Correspondence from attorneys Fitelson and Mayers related to lease issues.
    - Employment correspondence., 1953-1954. (Box 3, Folder 5)
      Correspondence regarding employment and casting related to the first run production.
    - Insurance., 1954-1956. (Box 3, Folder 6)
      Correspondence and documentation related to liability insurance and workers' compensation coverage.
    - Music licensing., 1954. (Box 3, Folder 7)
      Documentation related to the licensing of Weill's orchestration.
    - Clippings and marketing correspondence., 1952-1954. (Box 3, Folder 8)
      Clippings and correspondence related to advance advertising.
    - Blitzstein, Marc., 1954. (Box 3, Folder 9)
      Memo from Carmen Capalbo and unsigned, type-written letter.
    - Doubleday., 1954. (Box 3, Folder 10)
      Handwritten note to Doubleday.
    - Billing stubs and correspondence., 1954. (Box 3, Folder 11)
      Contents related to New York Telephone Company and Barnes Printing Company billing.
    - Dept. of Labor rating charges., 1954-1957. (Box 3, Folder 12)
      Notification of 'Experience Rating Charges' from the State of New York, Department of Labor.
    - Cast biographies., 1954. (Box 3, Folder 13)
      Type-written biographies of cast, some with photographs. Includes biographical materials on Brecht and Weill.
    - Payroll taxes and W-4s., 1954-1956. (Box 3, Folder 14)
      Correspondence, Department of Labor documentation, W-4s, personnel contact info and payroll audit sheets.
    - Press lists., 1954. (Box 3, Folder 15)
      Correspondence and documentation related to press invitations to performances.
    - Preview orders., 1954 March 8. (Box 3, Folder 16)
      Correspondence related to preview show.
    - Theater parties., 1954. (Box 4, Folder 1)
      Internal documentation, party contracts, seating charts and correspondence from the Theatre Party Bureau.
    - Union and crew., 1954-1956. (Box 4, Folder 2)
      Contracts, bond receipts and correspondence related to Union employees and management staff.
    - Theatre de Lys., 1954. (Box 4, Folder 3)
      Contracts, rental billing and correspondence from management company, Senior Estates Ltd.
    - Advertising agency., 1955-1956. (Box 4, Folder 4)
      Correspondence, internal memoranda ad rates and ad schedules.
    - Clippings, articles and advertisements., 1954-1959. (Box 4, Folder 5)
    - Opening night and preview lists., 1954. (Box 4, Folder 6)
      Correspondence and seating lists related to the opening night and preview shows. Includes letter from Richard Avedon.
    - Payroll., 1954. (Box 4, Folder 7)
      Payroll covers first run performance and rehearsals during week of 14 February through 6 June.
    - Props., 1954. (Box 4, Folder 8)
      Correspondence related to props.
    - Ad comps and marketing., 1955. (Box 4, Folder 9)
      Comps, printing examples and materials related to print advertisements.
    - Printing plates., ca. 1954. (Box 4, Folder 10)
      Original printing plates and print copy.
    - Blatas, Arbit., 1957. (Box 4, Folder 11)
      Invitations, correspondence, press release and programs related to Arbit Blatas Threepenny painting exhibit.
    - Correspondence re: audience fundraising., 1954-1958. (Box 4, Folder 12)
      Correspondence from members of audience and organizations interested in fundraising opportunities.
    - Budgets., 1955. (Box 5, Folder 1)
      Budgeting projection and planning.
    - Correspondence re: employment., 1955-1956. (Box 5, Folder 2)
      Correspondence relating to employment as crew and cast.
    - Flame-proofing affidavits., 1955-1956. (Box 5, Folder 3)
    - Outdoor marketing., 1956-1957. (Box 5, Folder 4)
      Correspondence, contracts and ad rate and placement portfolio.
    - Theatrical management., 1954-1957. (Box 5, Folder 5)
      Union contracts, correspondence and official documentation.
    - Associated Music Publishing., 1955-1956. (Box 5, Folder 6)
      Correspondence and billing statements related to licensing of Weill's score.
    - Box office taxes., 1955-1957. (Box 5, Folder 7)
      Correspondence and official documentation related to Federal and New York State taxes.
    - Electrical bills., 1955. (Box 5, Folder 8)
      Billing statements and correspondence.
    - Correspondence re: Fitelson and Mayers., 1955-1956. (Box 5, Folder 9)
      Legal correspondence related to numerous legal issues, including film versions of The Threepenny Opera.
    - Globe Ticket Company., 1955-1957. (Box 5, Folder 10)
      Correspondence, order statements and invoices.
    - Touring production., 1957. (Box 5, Folder 11)
      Correspondence and transcript of wire regarding plans to tour production.
    - Cast changes., 1957. (Box 5, Folder 12)
      Lists of changes to cast.
    - Department of Licenses., 1957. (Box 5, Folder 13)
      Correspondence regarding licensing of ticket sales.
    - Liability claims., 1956. (Box 5, Folder 14)
      Correspondence related to liability grievances claimed by members of the audience.
    - Magazines., 1955-1957. (Box 5, Folder 15)
      Magazines with articles related to the production.
    - Unemployment insurance., 1955. (Box 5, Folder 16)
      Correspondence, forms and handbook.
    - Management and employee issues., 1956-1958. (Box 5, Folder 17)
      Correspondence regarding various employees issues and general management of production.
    - De Lys rental., 1957. (Box 5, Folder 18)
      Correspondence regarding license renewal of theater.
    - Album sales and requests., 1955-1956. (Box 5, Folder 19)
      Sales statements, advertisement, Royalty earnings documentation and correspondence.
    - Dramatists Guild., 1955. (Box 5, Folder 20)
      Correspondence and contracts.
    - Theatre De Lys building repairs., 1956-1957. (Box 5, Folder 21)
      Correspondence and billing statements.
    - Copyright proceedings., 1929-1956. (Box 5, Folder 22)
      Correspondence and copies of exhibit evidence from case, plaintiffs Edmond Pauker and John Krimsky.
    - Playbills and mail order forms., 1960. (Box 5, Folder 23)
      Material related to the Marines' Theatre production.
    - Telegrams., 1960. (Box 5, Folder 24)
      Related to opening of Marines' Theatre run; included messages from Barry Levinson and Samuel Friedman.
    - Insurance and Workman's Compensation., 1954-1958. (Box 5, Folder 25)
      Insurance documentation, unemployment benefits claims, worker's compensation claims and policies, numerous forms and applications and injury reports and correspondence related to above materials.
    - Insurance and bond policies., 1955-1958. (Box 6, Folder 1)
      Insurance and bond policies and adjustment documentation.
    - Investors--Correspondence and financial distribution lists., 1955-1958. (Box 6, Folder 2)
      Correspondence and charts of investments and profit distributions regarding Threepenny Productions and Fortune Theater Company.
    - New Investors Agreement., 1955. (Box 6, Folder 3)
      Correspondence, contracts, and drafts of correspondence related to the second run production.
    - Second run investors' contracts., 1955. (Box 6, Folder 4)
      Drafts and contracts, some signed by investors, related to investors funding.
    - Mail orders., 1955. (Box 6, Folder 5-6)
      Daily total logs, some with receipts.
    - Mail orders., 1956. (Box 7, Folder 1-2)
    - Mail Orders--Accounting., 1955-1956. (Box 7, Folder 3)
      Accounting tablature, notes and documentation related to totals of mail orders.
    - Invitations--New Music Box., 1960. (Box 7, Folder 4)
      Invitations and mailing envelopes relating to the Hollywood premiere.
    - William Morris Agency, Inc., 1955-1957. (Box 7, Folder 5)
      Correspondence related to payment of weekly royalties.
    - Lotta Lenya and George Davis., 1955-1956. (Box 7, Folder 6)
      Correspondence and telegrams related to Ms. Lenya's role in the production.
    - League of New York Theatres., 1955. (Box 7, Folder 7)
      Correspondence, membership application and article of by-laws.
    - Musicians., 1954-1956. (Box 7, Folder 8)
      Correspondence, contracts and payment scales.
    - Matlowsky, Samuel (Musical Director)., 1954-1957. (Box 7, Folder 9)
    - Manufacturers Trust Bank., 1955-1956.; [3 folders]. (Box 7, Folder 10, Box 8)
      First two folders contain customer deposit receipts and the third folder contains contracts and correspondence related to business accounts held at bank.
    - Opening night comp tickets., 1955. (Box 8, Folder 3)
      Correspondence and lists related to tickets given away for opening night production.
    - Fuel oil bills., 1955-1957. (Box 8, Folder 4)
    - Operation and business plan., 1956. (Box 8, Folder 5)
      Outline of theater and business operations drafted by Zelda Dorfman, the production manager.
    - Production bills., 1955-1956. (Box 8, Folder 6-7)
    - Playbill., 1955. (Box 8, Folder 8)
      Bio drafts, drafts, correspondence, two photosgraphs, and playbills.
    - Payroll taxes., 1955-1956. (Box 8, Folder 9)
      Forms, quarterly payroll analysis documentation and official Dept. of Labor documentation.
    - Press lists., 1955. (Box 8, Folder 10-11)
      Press lists and correspondence related to the Bill Doll and Company, press agency for the production.
    - Barnes printing bills., 1955-1956. (Box 9, Folder 1)
      Billing statements, correspondence, and proofs.
    - Props and furniture., 1955. (Box 9, Folder 2)
      Correspondence related to props and furniture.
    - Personnel., 1955-1957. (Box 9, Folder 3)
      Correspondence relating to employment as crew and cast, salary lists, personnel lists.
    - Publicity., 1955-1957. (Box 9, Folder 4)
      Correspondence and memos to cast related to publicity functions.
    - Rehearsal and audition schedules., 1955. (Box 9, Folder 5)
    - Production bills--Rentals., 1955-1957. (Box 9, Folder 6)
      Correspondence and billing statements related to the rental of costumes, props and other related production equipment.
    - Dept. of Labor rating charges., 1955-1957. (Box 9, Folder 7)
      Notification of 'Experience Rating Charges' from the State of New York, Department of Labor and other documents from the Labor department.
    - Federal tax receipts., 1956-1957. (Box 9, Folder 8)
      Receipts indicating payment of Federal Tax from Manufacturers Trust Company.
    - Production bills--Telephone service., 1955-1957. (Box 9, Folder 9)
      Correspondence and billing statements related to telephone service.
    - Television production., 1955-1956. (Box 9, Folder 10)
      Correspondence and contracts related to attempted mounting of a television version of the off-Broadway production.
    - Union correspondence., 1955-1956. (Box 9, Folder 11)
      Correspondence and billing statements related to Union employees.
    - Theater parties., 1955-1956. (Box 9, Folder 12)
      Correspondence, contracts and lists related to theater parties.
    - Brandeis festival revivial., 1952. (Box 9, Folder 13)
      Clippings and ephemera related to the Leonard Bernstein revival at Brandeis, for which Marc Blitzstein fashioned an English adaptation.
    - Lucille Lortel publicity., 1955. (Box 9, Folder 14)
      Documents and drafts related to the second run production and new owners of the Theatre de Lys.
    - Chase, Stanley--Correspondence., 1960. (Box 9, Folder 15)
      Correspondence related to tax notice and advertising.
    - Threepenny Productions correspondence., 1962-1963. (Box 10, Folder 1)
      Assorted legal and business-related correspondence.
    - Scene and costume designer contracts., 1955. (Box 10, Folder 2)
    - Theatre de Lys contracts., 1956-1957. (Box 10, Folder 3)
    - Script--English adaptation by Marc Blitzstein., ca. 1955. (Box 10, Folder 4)
      Unpublished.
    - Script--English adaptation by Alan Howard., ca. 1955. (Box 10, Folder 5)
    - Script--English adaptation by David Vando., ca. 1955. (Box 10, Folder 6)
    - Beggar's Opera lyrics and score., 1956. (Box 10, Folder 7)
      Music and lyrics by Weill and Brecht, in German. Published.
    - Clippings., 1958. (Box 10, Folder 8)
      Assorted clippings from a news service.
    - Oversize photographs., ca. 1955-1960. (Box 71, Folder 1)
      Oversize black and white photographs of the cast on the set.